The sphere that I placed upon this land
ลูกบอลที่ฉันโยนลงมาสู่ผืนแผ่นดินนี้
took the form of a young man.
ได้เปลี่ยนร่างเป็นเด็กหนุ่ม
A girl from Ninannah, March,
"มาช" สาวน้อยแห่งนินันนา
named "it", "Fushi".
ตั้งชื่อให้ "เจ้าสิ่งนั้น" ว่า "ฟุชิ"
Through the battle with the Spirit Bear,
หลังการต่อสู้กับโอนิกุมะ
it received stimulation
ฟุชิก็ได้รับแรงกระตุ้นใหม่
and collected new information.
และทำการเก็บข้อมูลได้สำเร็จ
Thank you.
ขอบคุณ
TO YOUR ETERNITY
แด่เธอผู้เป็นนิรันดร์
Listen.
ฟังให้ดีนะ
Let's play a game where you try not to be found by anyone.
นี่เป็นเกมห้ามให้ใครหาเจอ
The game will continue until I come back, so stay hidden until then.
ก่อนพี่จะกลับมา พาโรน่าต้องแอบอยู่ที่นี่นะ
Got it?
เข้าใจไหม
Sister...
พี่คะ...
Here's some food.
นี่เสบียงนะ
If you run out, pick some berries and fruits.
ถ้ากินหมดแล้วก็ไปหาผลไม้กินแทนนะ
Sister!
พีคะ
If you win, I'll make a new doll for you!
พอเกมจบแล้ว พี่จะทำตุ๊กตาตัวใหม่ให้นะ
Parona, wherever have you been?
พาโรน่า เธอหายไปไหนมาทั้งอาทิตย์เลย
Where is my sister?
พี่สาวล่ะคะ
She's not here anymore.
พี่เขาไม่อยู่แล้ว
She was chosen as the sacrifice for the Spirit Bear.
เขาถูกเลือกให้เป็นเครื่องบรรณาการของท่านโอนิกุมะ
Sister...
พี่คะ
Running away?
น่าอับอายจริงๆ
-Sister! -Pathetic.
-พี่คะ -กล้าหนีพิธีไปได้ยังไง
And you call yourself a woman of the Ninannah?
ยังเรียกตัวเองว่าเป็นสตรีแห่งนินันนาได้อีกเหรอ
Sister!
พี่คะ
You are no longer one of us!
เธอไม่ใช่คนของที่นี่อีกต่อไป
Scram! Leave this place!
ไสหัวไปให้ไกลเลย
It was a dream...
ฝันเหรอ...
What kind of face did my sister have on back then?
สีหน้าของพี่สาวในตอนนั้น เป็นยังไงกันแน่นะ
EPISODE FOUR A LARGE VESSEL
ตอนที่ 4 ภาชนะมหึมา
Thank you.
ขอบคุณ
What a weird puppy!
เจ้าหมาน้อยนี่แปลกมากเลย
Here!
เอ้านี่
Thank you.
ขอบคุณ
How much longer will we be traveling?
ต้องเดินทางอีกนานแค่ไหนกัน
We should reach Yanome in roughly 20 days.
จากนี่ไปยาโนเมะต้องใช้เวลาอย่างน้อย 20 วัน
You're the Shaman of Yanome, aren't you?
คุณคือแม่หมอแห่งยาโนเมะนี่
Why are you in the same dirty carriage as us?
ทำไมถึงมานั่งเกวียนเดียวกับพวกเราล่ะ
That's right! You did horrible things to March!
คุณสินะ คนที่ทำเรื่องไม่ดีกับมาช
Why did you choose me?
ทำไมต้องเลือกมาชด้วย
You were the prettiest, that's why.
เพราะเธอเป็นเด็กที่สวยที่สุดไง
I... I see.
จริง...จริงเหรอ
Look.
ดูนี่นะ
I am a criminal.
ฉันเป็นแค่นักโทษ
To achieve their greedy ambitions,
เพื่อสนองความโลภของพวกเขา
they were desperate enough to enlist the help of a fake shaman.
เลยใช้แม่หมอตัวปลอมช่วยพวกเขาฆ่าคน
Desperate?
ความโลภเหรอ
They want the abundance of the land of Ninannah.
ยาโนเมะปรารถนาในแผ่นดินอันอุดมสมบูรณ์ของนินันนา
That is why they are so absorbed in Ninannah's tradition and the sacrifice ritual.
ถึงได้เข้ามาแทรกแซงพิธีสังเวยของชาวนินันนา
They clear their suspicion by dirtying their own hands in the ritual, sending presents and thanks to give the ritual an air of heroism.
เข้ามาช่วยประกอบพิธี และมอบทรัพยากรเป็นการขอบคุณ
"Oh, people of Ninannah, how well you have devoted yourselves...
ทำเป็นพูดว่า "ขอบคุณชาวนินันนาทุกท่านที่เสียสละ"
to the betterment of all people on this earth!"
"ทำให้ทุกคนรอดพ้นจากภัยของโอนิกุมะ"
The goal that lies beyond that dynamic
แต่เป้าหมายที่แท้จริงคือ
is psychological conquering and domination.
การควบคุมและรุกล้ำจิตวิญญาณ
I wasn't aware...
ฉันไม่เคยรู้มาก่อนเลย...
It's unpleasant that all of this arose from one word of tradition.
พิธีที่สืบทอดกันมานาน พิธีที่อ้างประเพณีมากลบเกลื่อนความกลัวนี้น่ะ
The fact that this ritual already existed is even more abhorrent.
ฉันรู้สึกเกลียดมาโดยตลอด
Oh, my!
น่าแปลกใจจริงๆ
I had thought that the people of Ninannah were folks who believe that faith is more important than the lives of their brethren.
ฉันนึกว่าชาวนินันนาจะเป็นพวกที่
They are antiquated adults.
มีแต่พวกผู้ใหญ่หัวโบราณเท่านั้นแหละที่คิดแบบนี้
They are indifferent to the souls of the suffering.
พวกเขาไม่แยแสคนที่ต้องมารับเคราะห์เลยด้วยซ้ำ
This backward practice needs to be put to an end as soon as possible.
ความเชื่อเน่าเฟะแบบนั้นควรถูกกำจัดไปให้สิ้นซาก
That is impossible.
เป็นไปไม่ได้หรอก
The older people of Ninannah are fixated in their ways.
คนเฒ่าคนแก่ของนินันนาคร่ำครึมาก
They won't believe you even if you tell them "God" is dead.
ถึงจะบอกพวกเขาว่า "เทพตายไปแล้ว" พวกเขาก็ไม่เชื่อกันหรอก
"God"?
"เทพ" งั้นเหรอ
What should I do?
แล้วฉันควรทำยังไงล่ะ
Ah! No! No!
ไม่ได้นะ ไม่ได้
What happened?
เกิดอะไรขึ้น
It's wet and stinky!
ทั้งเปียกทั้งเหม็นเลย
It's flowing this way!
ไหลมานี่แล้ว
Let's clean you up, puppy.
เจ้าหมาน้อย มาอาบน้ำกันเถอะ
It's cold but be brave!
ถึงจะเย็นมากก็เถอะ แต่ไม่ต้องกลัวไปนะ
Don't...
แกต้อง...
ever…
จดจำฉัน...
forget about me.
ไปตลอดเลยนะ
-What? -Huh?
อะไรกัน
It was you all along!
นายเองเหรอ
I missed you!
ฉันคิดถึงนายมากเลย
Do you know this guy?
เธอรู้จักเจ้านี่ด้วยเหรอ
His name's Fushi.
อื้อ เขาชื่อ "ฟุชิ" แหละ
The sun is setting. It's time to go.
พระอาทิตย์ใกล้ตกดินแล้ว ไปกันได้แล้วค่ะ
Fushi!
ไม่ได้นะฟุจัง
Come with March!
ไปกับมาชเดี๋ยวนี้เลย
Good boy.
เป็นเด็กดีจังเลย
I'll teach you how to use the bathroom later.
ไว้เดี๋ยวจะสอนว่าต้องเข้าห้องน้ำยังไงนะ
It seems to be close with you, March.
เขาสนิทกับมาชมากเลยเหรอ
Fushi is still a child.
ฟุจังยังเป็นเด็กน้อยอยู่
That's why March decided she will be Fushi's mom!
มาชเลยว่าจะเป็นแม่จ๋าให้ฟุจังเอง
He can't "die". So that's why his name is Fushi?
เพราะเขาเป็นอมตะเลยตั้งชื่อว่า "ฟุชิ" สินะ
A person who can't die is unfortunate.
การที่ตายไม่ได้ถือว่าโชคร้ายมากเลยนะ
I feel people's lives have a purpose to them.
ฉันคิดว่าชีวิตที่จำกัดของมนุษย์ ก็มีข้อดีของมันอยู่
In living infinitely,
แต่เขามีชีวิตที่ไม่จำกัดแบบนี้
what meaning will he find in living?
จะเข้าใจถึงความหมายของการมีชีวิตอยู่ได้ไหมนะ
Meaning?
ความหมายเหรอ
Sorry, March.
ขอโทษด้วย
It's wrong to look for meaning in life and death.
ฉันไม่ควรวิจารณ์ความเป็นความตายของคนอื่นแบบนี้
I don't understand what you're saying,
ถึงจะฟังไม่เข้าใจก็เถอะ
but March is very happy right now!
แต่ตอนนี้มาชมีความสุขมากเลยล่ะ
Please wear this.
กรุณาใส่มันด้วยค่ะ
Yanome clothes.
นี่มันชุดของชาวยาโนเมะนี่
There are clothes for Fushi too!
มีของฟุจังด้วย
I'll put them on for you.
เดี๋ยวฉันใส่ให้นะ
Here we go!
เอาล่ะนะ
What will happen to us now?
ต่อจากนี้พวกเราอาจถูกคุกคามก็ได้
From today onwards,
ตั้งแต่นี้ต่อไป
you are Parona and March of the Yanome.
พวกคุณคือมาชและพาโรน่าแห่งยาโนเมะ
Look, big sister!
พี่สาวดูสิ
There's a lot of tasty-looking stuff!
มีของน่าอร่อยเต็มไปหมดเลย
There are so many pretty things too!
แถมยังมีของสวย ๆ เยอะแยะไปหมด
Please help yourselves to what you like.
อยากทานอะไรก็ทานได้ตามใจเลยนะคะ
I'll pay.
ฉันจ่ายให้เองค่ะ
Really?
จริงเหรอ
Mm... It smells good!
หอมจังเลย
Do you have something you'd like to tell your loved ones?
มีอะไรอยากบอกกับคนสำคัญบ้างหรือเปล่า
Let us help you! We are a letter shop!
ไปรษณีย์ ไปรษณีย์อยู่ทางนี้นะครับ
-Look, big sister! -We can deliver your messages for you.
-พี่สาวดูนั่นสิ -ผมช่วยส่งสารได้นะ
Welcome.
ยินดีต้อนรับจ้ะ
Please write your message on this piece of paper.
เขียนสิ่งที่อยากบอก สารที่อยากส่ง ลงบนกระดาษนี้ได้เลย
Write?
เขียนเหรอ
Oh, I see. Don't worry.
อ้อ จริงสิ ไม่ต้องกังวลไปนะ
I'll help you write it down. Please tell me what you'd like to say.
เดี๋ยวฉันช่วยเขียนให้เอง ว่ามาเลย
Then...
งั้นก็...
Mother, father, how are you?
พ่อจ๋าแม่จ๋า สบายดีไหมจ๊ะ
March is in Yanome right now.
ตอนนี้มาชอยู่ที่ยาโนเมะ
Please don't worry about me!
ไม่ต้องเป็นห่วงนะ
That's all.
แค่นี้แหละ
Okay.
โอเค
Where should I deliver this to?
แล้ว...จะให้ส่งไปที่ไหนล่ะ
To my parents!
ส่งไปให้พ่อจ๋าแม่จ๋า
They are in Ninannah.
พวกเขาอยู่ที่นินันนา
Ninannah?
นินันนาเหรอ
The Ninannah where the Spirit Bear lives?
นินันนาที่เป็นดินแดนศักดิ์สิทธิ์ ของท่านโอนิกุมะน่ะเหรอ
That's right!
ใช่แล้ว
The Ninannah has no written script.
นินันนาไม่มีการใช้ตัวอักษร
Your parents
พ่อแม่ของคุณมาช
will not be able to understand what is written in the letter, March.
ไม่เข้าใจเนื้อหาบนจดหมายนี้หรอกค่ะ
But March knows a different script!
แต่มาชรู้ตัวอักษรหลายตัวนะ
Is that so? What kind?
งั้นเหรอคะ อักษรอะไรกันนะ
This!
อันนี้ไง
And what does that mean?
แล้วมันแปลว่าอะไรคะนั่น
It means "March is very well!"
แปลว่า "มาชสบายดี" ไงล่ะ
March.
มาช
Please help me deliver this!
ช่วยส่งให้หน่อยนะ
All right.
ได้เลย
Where should I put it in Ninannah?
จะให้ส่งไปที่ไหนในนินันนาล่ะ
Where my parents live, of course!
ที่ที่พ่อจ๋าแม่จ๋าอยู่ไง
Which district? Which block?
เธอพอจะรู้ที่อยู่ไหมล่ะ
Whose jurisdiction?
เป็นเขตปกครองของใคร
Do you know, big sister?
พี่สาวรู้ไหม
No.
ไม่รู้
Ninannah is a large territory.
นินันนาใหญ่มากนะ
Even in the closest region, there are over 40 villages.
ที่ใกล้ที่นี่ที่สุดก็มีตั้ง 40 ชนเผ่าแล้ว
What is that picture?
นั่นคือภาพอะไรเหรอคะ
March, let's go and have dinner.
คุณมาชคะ พวกเราไปทานมื้อค่ำกันดีกว่าค่ะ
I'll hold onto this for you.
ฉันจะเก็บจดหมายนี่ไว้ให้เอง
We'll come back when we figure it out.
ไว้รู้ที่อยู่พ่อจ๋าแม่จ๋าแล้ว เราค่อยมากันใหม่นะ
Okay.
ก็ได้
What is this? It's so yummy!
นี่คืออะไรเหรอ อร่อยมากเลย
Look at the way she eats.
ดูท่ากินเขาสิ
Thank you...
ขอบคุณ...
Fushi, you should eat properly.
ตอนกินข้าวต้องกินดี ๆ นะฟุชิ
I've taught you before.
เคยสอนไปแล้วไงว่า
You have to eat with your hands.
ต้องใช้มือกินแบบนี้
Got it?
เข้าใจหรือยัง
March, you should exercise manners as well.
คุณมาชกินได้ดีกว่านี้อีกนะคะ
Why don't you try using those chopsticks on your head?
ลองใช้ตะเกียบบนหัวดู ดีไหมคะ
Chopsticks?
ตะเกียบเหรอ
These are "head scratchers"!
นี่มัน "ไม้เกาหัว" ต่างหาก
They're used to scratch your head when it itches!
เครื่องมือที่ใช้เกาเวลาคันหัวโดยเฉพาะ
It seems that Yanome's culture has not been properly propagated.
ดูเหมือนวัฒนธรรมยาโนเมะที่เผยแพร่ เข้าไปยังนินันนาจะถูกเปลี่ยนไปเยอะเลยนะคะ
I apologize. Please continue as you have been eating.
ฉันเสียมารยาทเอง คุณกินแบบเดิมเถอะค่ะ
Fushi, eat as you please.
ฟุชิกินแบบที่ตัวเองชอบได้เลยนะ
Fushi, are you all right?
ไม่เป็นไรใช่ไหมฟุชิ
I think he has learned Yanome's table manners.
เหมือนเขาจะเรียนรู้ มารยาทบนโต๊ะอาหารของยาโนเมะได้แล้ว
What do you think, March?
รู้สึกยังไงบ้างคะคุณมาช
Yanome is a good place, isn't it?
ยาโนเมะเป็นที่ที่ดีมาก
A place where you could spend the rest of your life.
คุ้มค่าที่จะอยู่ไปตลอดชีวิตเลยใช่ไหมคะ
Not really...
ไม่เห็นรู้สึกเลย
March thinks...
มาชรู้สึกว่า...
March?
มาช
A pity.
น่าเสียดายจริง ๆ
As expected, morning glory from the west works wonders.
ดอกผักบุ้งได้ผลจริง ๆ ด้วย
As I previously reported,
ตามที่ฉันได้เล่าไป
during the iteration of this ritual which has been conducted for many years,
ในระหว่างการทำพิธีที่สืบต่อกันมานาน
we caught sight of and subsequently captured the Spirit Bear.
ฉันได้เห็นท่านโอนิกุมะกับตาตัวเองครั้งแรก จึงนำตัวกลับมาด้วย
In addition, I have something to show all of you.
และมีอีกสิ่งหนึ่งที่อยากให้ทุกท่านได้เห็นค่ะ
This boy.
เด็กหนุ่มคนนี้แหละค่ะ
As we were returning from the ritual,
ตอนที่กำลังจะเดินทางกลับหลังเสร็จพิธี
we witnessed this boy take down the Spirit Bear.
พวกเราก็ได้เห็นเด็กหนุ่มคนนี้ ล้มท่านโอนิกุมะเองกับตา
This boy felled the Spirit Bear?
เจ้าหนุ่มนั่นล้มโอนิกุมะงั้นเหรอ
Yes. He is immortal.
ใช่ค่ะ เขามีร่างกายที่เป็นอมตะ
Move!
เดินไป
If I kill you, they'll let me out!
แค่ต้องฆ่าแกให้ตาย ฉันก็จะเป็นอิสระแล้ว
The wound... disappeared?
แผลหายไปแล้ว
How could it be?
เป็นไปได้ยังไง
It hurts! Ow...
โอ๊ย เจ็บ ๆ...
Hurts... Ow...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ ๆ...
Don't blame me, little runt!
อย่าโทษกันเลยนะพ่อหนุ่ม
I just want to meet my love and enjoy good food and live my life!
ฉันแค่อยากออกไปจากที่นี่ ไปกินข้าวกับคนรักของฉัน
-It hurts... -Please die!
-โอ๊ยเจ็บ... -ช่วยตายไปสักทีเถอะนะ
It hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
Is he a "God" or is he a demon?
เขาเป็นเทพ หรือเป็นปีศาจกันนะ
We have no idea as of right now.
มันชัดเจนมากค่ะ
We have yet to ascertain his capabilities.
แต่ฉันคิดว่า
But I am convinced
พลังของเขายังระบุขีดจำกัดไม่ได้
that this boy is critical to the future of the Yanome.
ถือเป็นบุคคลที่ยาโนเมะต้องการอย่างมากในอนาคต
Get out of the way, grandma!
หลบไปยาย
Cut his head off!
ตัดหัวหมอนี่เลย
It hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
Fushi!
ฟุจัง
-March, please calm it down. -It hurts...
-คุณมาช ช่วยทำให้เขาอยู่ในความสงบด้วยค่ะ -โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
Hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ
Please bear with it.
ทนหน่อยนะ
I won't forgive...
ยกโทษให้ไม่ได้เด็ดขาด
whoever did this to you!
กล้าทำกับนายแบบนี้ได้ยังไง
There we go...
โอ๋ ๆ เด็กดี...
There, you're all better now!
ดีมาก หายแล้ว
You did great, Fushi!
เก่งมากเลยนะ ฟุจัง
March!
มาช
Are you with Fushi?
เธออยู่กับฟุชิเหรอ
Big sister? Where are you?
พี่สาวเหรอ พี่อยู่ไหนน่ะ
I'm here, March!
อยู่นี่จ้ะ มาช
Big sister!
พี่สาว
What do you have in that room?
ตรงที่เธออยู่มีอะไรบ้าง
There's some straw and a bowl.
มีฟางกับกาน้ำ
And this.
แล้วก็อันนี้
Good. Tie it onto this.
เยี่ยม ผูกมันกับเชือกนี้เลย
Where are we?
ที่ไหนคือที่ไหนเหรอ
What's going to happen to us?
พวกเราจะเป็นยังไงกันต่อเหรอ
Don't worry, March.
ไม่ต้องห่วงนะมาช
Could you get me some of Fushi's fur?
อ้อจริงสิ ช่วยเก็บขนของฟุจังให้ฉันหน่อยได้ไหม
Fushi's fur?
ของของฟุจังเหรอ
Right. To the right.
ไปทางขวาหน่อย แบบนั้นแหละ
Uncle!
คุณลุงคะ
When will March be able to leave this place?
พวกเราจะได้ออกไปเมื่อไหร่เหรอ
You'll be here forever.
อยู่ในนี้ไปทั้งชีวิตเถอะ
It hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
What's wrong? Haven't your wounds healed?
เป็นอะไรไป แผลนายหายดีแล้วไม่ใช่เหรอ
Hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
Fushi?
ฟุจัง
What is this?
คืออะไรล่ะเนี่ย
Hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ
An arrow...
ลูกธนูนี่นา
So many of them...
มีเยอะขนาดนี้เลยเหรอ
How pitiful... If we don't help it...
น่าสงสารจัง ต้องรีบรักษาแผลให้แล้วสิ
How is it coming along?
ได้เรื่องยังไงบ้าง
Well, nobody wants to tend to the Spirit Bear.
ไม่มีใครยอมดูแลท่านโอนิกุมะเลยครับ
What's so difficult about looking after a bear?
แค่ดูแลหมีตัวหนึ่ง มันจะไปยากอะไรนักหนา
Then, let her do it.
ให้เขาดูแลแล้วกัน
Is it all right? It's dangerous.
จะดีเหรอครับ มันอันตรายมากเลยนะ
It doesn't matter.
ไม่เป็นไรหรอก
There's no issue to be had
อย่างมากก็แค่มีเด็กตายไปคนหนึ่ง
with some girl dying.
ไม่ใช่เรื่องใหญ่อะไร
I can't believe they left the bear in your care.
พวกเขาจะให้เธอไปดูแลหมีนั่นเนี่ยนะ
It's too dangerous for you to do it all by yourself.
เธอตัวคนเดียวมันอันตรายเกินไป
I'll be fine. I have Fushi and Kanitarou with me.
มีฟุชิกับคานิทาโร่อยู่ด้วย มาชไม่เป็นไรหรอก
Big sister, you have your work too.
อีกอย่าง พี่สาวก็มีงานทำความสะอาดต้องทำ
You have to do your best too!
สู้ ๆ นะ
Right.
จ้ะ
But...
แต่ว่า...
Don't worry! It'll be all right!
ไม่ต้องห่วงนะ
First, we'll have the old woman fake illness to trick the Yanome.
อันดับแรกให้คุณยายแกล้งป่วยหลอกพวกยาโนเมะ
Help! I'm dying!
ช่วยด้วย ฉันจะตายอยู่แล้ว
Then, I'll go save March.
แล้วก็ไปช่วยมาช
-Yay! -Run!
-เยี่ยมเลย -รีบหนีกันเถอะ
Then, kill the Spirit Bear.
จากนั้นก็ฆ่าโอนิกุมะ
And bring back its eyes or fur as proof.
และเอาตาหรือขนของมันกลับไปเป็นหลักฐาน
The people of Ninannah will know that there is no longer a need
พอชาวนินันนาเห็นแล้วก็จะเข้าใจเอง
to continue with the ritual.
ไม่จำเป็นต้องมี "พิธี" อีกต่อไป
That should work.
แผนนี้น่าจะใช้ได้
No... No matter what...
ไม่สิ ไม่ว่ายังไง...
I have to do it.
ต้องทำตามนี้ให้ได้
Right, sister?
ใช่ไหมคะพี่
Hey, big bear... You're just like me, aren't you?
แกก็คงเหมือนกับฉันสินะ
When March left Ninannah,
ตอนที่ฉันออกมาจากนินันนา
everyone told me how good of a girl I was. Saying "thanks" and "congratulations"...
ทุกคนบอกว่าฉันเก่งและพิเศษมาก
But in the end, I'm just a normal girl.
ทั้ง ๆ ที่ฉันก็เป็นแค่เด็กหญิงธรรมดาคนหนึ่ง
Hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
You're just a bear who likes human meat.
ฉันว่ารู้ว่าแกก็เป็นแค่หมีที่ชอบกินเนื้อคน
People made a big fuss over you and shot you with arrows...
-ทำให้ผู้คนกังวลแล้วก็ถูกธนูยิงเป็นแผลไปทั้งตัว -โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
And they made you out to be like the real scary Spirit Bear...
-เลยต้องกลายมาเป็นท่านโอนิกุมะที่คนเกรงกลัว
Once your wounds heal, you'll be able to go back.
รอแผลหายแล้ว แกต้องได้กลับบ้านแน่
Go back...
ต้องได้กลับแน่...
Ah, sorry for making you worry.
โทษทีนะ ทำให้แกกังวลไปด้วย
Sorry...
ขอโทษนะ
There, there...
โอ๋ ๆ เด็กดี...
Hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ...
Thank... you...
ข...ขอบ...คุณนะ
And so the vessel opened.
ภาชนะได้ถูกเปิดออกแล้ว
The Spirit Bear is dead.
โอนิกุมะตายแล้ว
Its body will be disposed of tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้คงมีคนมาเก็บร่างไป
I must ensure that I have evidence before we escape from here.
ก่อนถึงตอนนั้น ฉันต้องรีบเก็บหลักฐานและหนีไปให้ได้
March will be able to get out of here soon.
มาช เดี๋ยวก็จะได้ออกไปแล้วนะ
She doesn't have to grow up here.
เธอจะต้องไม่เติบโตเป็นผู้ใหญ่อยู่ที่นี่
Over there should do it...
ตรงนั้นน่าจะพอได้
Sister!
พี่คะ
Hurts...
โอ๊ยเจ็บ
This is... The tool room?
ที่นี่...ห้องเก็บของงั้นเหรอ
I wondered what fell.
ฉันก็นึกว่าอะไรตกลงมา
So it was you.
ที่แท้ก็เธอเองเหรอ
I can help you keep this a secret.
เรื่องที่เธอคิดหนีน่ะ ฉันช่วยเก็บเป็นความลับได้นะ
But you better be quiet...
ถ้าทำตัวเชื่อง ๆ น่ะนะ
How dare you...
นี่เธอกล้า...
Shut up and stay still.
เงียบซะ ทำตัวให้เชื่อง ๆ หน่อย
Rotate out.
เปลี่ยนเวร
What is going on...
มีเรื่องอะไร...เหรอคะ
I'm taking you away.
ฉันจะพาตัวเธอไป
Sister.
พี่คะ
You must've been smiling back then, right?
ใบหน้าของพี่ในตอนนั้น คงมีรอยยิ้มอยู่ใช่ไหมคะ
That is why I will use the life that you've given me
ฉันได้รับชีวิตที่พี่ปกป้องเอาไว้ให้ฉัน
with purpose.
และใช้มันในทางที่ถูกต้อง
Let's get out of here together!
หนีไปด้วยกันเถอะ
Big sister!
พี่สาว
Parona and the others
พวกของพาโรน่าตัดสินใจที่จะทำตาม
are planning to escape from Yanome.
แผนแหกคุกเพื่อกลับไปยังนินันนา
However, the Yanome soldiers lead by Hayase
ทว่า ฮายาเสะได้นำกองทหารยาโนเมะ
are persistent.
ไปขัดขวางพวกเขาอย่างไม่ปรานี
During the escape,
ระหว่างทางหนีตายที่แสนทรหด
Fushi's body...
ร่างของฟุชิ
"EPISODE FIVE: THOSE WHO ACCOMPANY YOU" faces another change.
"ตอนที่ 5 ผู้ร่วมทาง" ก็เกิดการเปลี่ยนแปลงอีกครั้ง